Guide to the Washington Science Teachers Association Records 1959-2004
Western Washington University, Center for Pacific Northwest Studies
Washington Science Teachers Association Records
1959-2004
Center for Pacific Northwest Studies Goltz-Murray Building 808 25th St Bellingham, WA 98225-9123 Phone: 360 650 7534 Email: cpnws@wwu.edu
XOE_CPNWS0034wsta
Washington Science Teachers Association
3 Linear Feet.
The Washington Science Teachers Association collection contains historical information on the origins and activities of this educational association in Washington State. The materials date from the year of the association’s formation in 1959 to the last journal publication in 2004. The bulk of the contents are administrative records and publications. There are also conference and club activities materials that document the interactions of the WSTA among different communities in Washington.
The Washington Science Teachers Association formed in 1959 at Jones Hall, College of Puget Sound (now U.P.S.) with the intent of promoting better science education programs in the state of Washington. The WSTA is governed by a written constitution and administered through an elected executive board. In 1961, the WSTA established a long standing collaboration with the National Science Teachers Association.
In 1961, the WSTA developed in-service days for teachers and administrators in the state of Washington to share their teaching innovations. In addition to hosting workshops for science teachers, the WSTA has also granted a number of outstanding science “teacher of the year” awards to recognize dedication and creativity in teachers for K-12 schools. The WSTA also hosts an annual Science and Engineering Contest in the state of Washington for K-12 students.
In 1972, the WSTA established a professional journal. The content and issue of the WSTA journal is strictly controlled by teachers, and serves as a venue for sharing experiments, teaching hints, and opinions. The journal also discusses relevant science issues, and announces up and coming conferences and other events for science teachers.
The Washington Science Teachers Association collection contains historical information on the origins and activities of this educational association in Washington State. The materials date from the year of the association’s formation in 1959 to the last journal publication in 2004. The bulk of the contents are administrative records and publications. There are also conference and club activities materials that document the interactions of the WSTA among different communities in Washington.
The WSTA administrative records contain correspondence from 1959 to 1989. Also included are constitutions and by-laws, membership lists, minutes of meetings, lists of officers and elections, and reports. Information on the WSTA's efforts to improve science education for K-12 schools is included in the reports and correspondence.
The publications include newsletters and journals that are focused on science and education in the state of Washington.
The Washington Science Teachers Association Records are organized in accordance with the following series and sub-series arrangement:
Series I: Administrative Records 1959-2004
1. General, 1959-1989
2. Minutes, 1959-1984
3. Reports, 1959-1980
4. Conference Materials, 1959-1989
5. Club Activities, 1959-2004
Series II: Newsletters and Publications
1. Newsletters, 1962-1972
2. Journals, 1972-2004
Robert Christman donated the Washington Science Teachers Association Records to the Center for Pacific Northwest Studies in May 2004.
Editions of the Washington Science Teachers Association journal are available at the Western Washington University library.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Washington Science Teachers Association
Science education--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Science--Study and teaching--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Science--Study and teaching--Periodicals.; Science--Study and teaching (Elementary)--Washington (State)--History--Sources.; Science--Study and teaching (Elementary)--United States.; Science teachers--United States--Periodicals.
Washington (State); Science
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.
- Administrative Records, 1959-2004; Series I
  - General, 1959-1989; Sub-series 1
    - Origins of WSTA, 1959 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Constitutions and Bylaws, 1959-1977 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1974 (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Correspondence, 1975-1989 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - “A Short History of the WSTA” by Wallace R. Drake, 1980 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Officers and Elections of WSTA, 1960-1980 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - WSTA Membership Lists, 1959-1967 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Minutes, 1959-1984; Sub-series 2
    - Meeting Minutes, 1959 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1965- 1969 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1970-1974 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1975- 1979 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Meeting Minutes, 1980- 1984 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - Reports, 1959-1980; Sub-series 3
    - Executive Secretary’s Reports, 1959-1982 (Box-folder 1/14)
    - Treasurer’s Reports, 1959-1974 (Box-folder 1/15)
    - Treasurer’s Reports, 1975-1984 (Box-folder 1/16)
    - Registrar’s Reports, 1976-1980 (Box-folder 1/17)
    - Editor’s Reports, 1974- 1979 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Journal Reports, 1972-1981 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Resolutions, 1970-1976 (Box-folder 1/20)
    - General Administrative Reports, 1968-1980 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Conference Materials, 1959-1989; Sub-series 4
    - Materials, 1959-1969 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - Materials, 1970-1979 (Box-folder 1/23)
    - Materials, 1980-1989 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Club Activities, 1959-2004; Sub-series 5
    - Letterheads and Official Forms, 1959-2004 (Box-folder 1/25)
    - Awards and Recognition, 1959-1981 (Box-folder 1/26)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1974-1979 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - Surveys and Guidelines for Teachers (WSTA), 1959-2004 (Box-folder 1/28)
- Publications, 1962-2004; Series II
  - Newsletters, 1962-1972; Sub-series 1
    - WSTA Newsletters Vol.1 to Vol. 6, 1962-1967 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - WSTA Newsletters Vol.7 to Vol. 12, No. 1, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 2/2)
  - Journals, 1972-2004; Sub-series 2
    - Vol.12, No.2, 1972 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Vol.13, No. 1-4, 1973 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Vol.14, No. 1-4, 1974 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - Vol.15, No. 1-4, 1975 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Vol.16, No. 1-4, 1976 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Vol.17, No. 1-4, 1977 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Vol.18, No. 1-4, 1978 (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Vol.19, No. 1-4, 1979 (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Vol.20, No. 1-4, 1980 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Vol.21, No. 1-4, 1981 (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Vol.22, No. 1-4, 1982 (Box-folder 2/13)
    - Vol.23, No. 1-4, 1983 (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Vol.24, No. 1-4, 1984 (Box-folder 2/15)
    - Vol.25, No. 1-4, 1985 (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Vol.26, No. 1-4, 1986 (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Vol.27, No. 1-4, 1987 (Box-folder 2/18)
    - Vol.28, No. 1-4, 1988 (Box-folder 2/19)
    - Vol.29, No. 1-4, 1989 (Box-folder 2/20)
    - Vol.30, No. 1-4, 1990 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Vol.31, No. 1-4, 1991 (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Vol.32, No. 1-4, 1992 (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Vol.33, No. 1-4, 1993 (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Vol.34, No. 1-4, 1994 (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Vol.35, No. 1-4, 1995 (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Vol.36, No. 1-4, 1996 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Vol.37, No. 1-4, 1997 (Box-folder 3/8)
    - Vol.38, No. 1-4, 1998 (Box-folder 3/9)
    - Vol.39, No. 1-4, 1999 (Box-folder 3/10)
    - Vol.40, No. 1-4, 2000 (Box-folder 3/11)
    - Vol.41, No. 1-4, 2001 (Box-folder 3/12)
    - Vol.42, No. 1-4, 2002 (Box-folder 3/13)
    - Vol.43, No. 1-4, 2003 (Box-folder 3/14)
    - Vol.44, No. 1-4, 2004 (Box-folder 3/15)